<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Health and medicine &#8211; UW News</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.washington.edu/news/category/health-and-medicine/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.washington.edu/news</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 23:08:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.3</generator>
	<item>
		<title>3D imaging method may help doctors better determine prostate cancer aggressiveness</title>
		<link>https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/12/09/3d-imaging-method-may-help-doctors-better-determine-prostate-cancer-aggressiveness/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sarah McQuate]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 18:17:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health and medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[College of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Bioengineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Mechanical Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Liu]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lawrence True]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.washington.edu/news/?p=76757</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A team led by the UW has developed a new, non-destructive method that images entire 3D biopsies instead of a slice for determining prostate cancer aggressiveness. The 3D images provided more information than a 2D image — specifically, details about the tree-like structure of the glands throughout the tissue.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_76759" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="width: 760px"><a href="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/12/09094038/S6-screenshot.png"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full-content wp-image-76759" src="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/12/09094038/S6-screenshot-750x391.png" alt="Two volume renderings (drawings that highlight features on microscopy data) are labeled in yellow (the outer walls of the gland) and red (the fluid-filled space inside the gland). The top drawing, labeled &quot;cancer,&quot; shows a lot more yellow and smaller, more intricate glands. The bottom drawing, labeled &quot;benign&quot; shows larger glands with a lot more fluid-filled space inside the glands. " width="750" height="391" srcset="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/12/09094038/S6-screenshot-750x391.png 750w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/12/09094038/S6-screenshot-300x156.png 300w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/12/09094038/S6-screenshot-1024x534.png 1024w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/12/09094038/S6-screenshot-375x195.png 375w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/12/09094038/S6-screenshot-1140x594.png 1140w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/12/09094038/S6-screenshot.png 1516w" sizes="(max-width: 750px) 100vw, 750px" /></a></p>
<p class="wp-caption-text">A team led by the University of Washington has developed a new, non-destructive method that images entire 3D biopsies instead of a slice. The 3D images provided more information than a 2D image — specifically, details about the tree-like structure of the glands throughout the tissue. Shown here is a screenshot of a volume rendering of glands in two 3D biopsy samples from prostates (yellow: the outer walls of the gland; red: the fluid-filled space inside the gland). The cancer sample (top) shows smaller and more densely packed glands compared to the benign tissue sample (bottom).<span class="wp-media-credit">Xie et al./Cancer Research</span></span></p>
</div>
<p>Prostate cancer is the <a href="https://www.cancer.gov/types/prostate">most common cancer for men</a> and, for men in the United States, it&#8217;s the second leading cause of death.</p>
<p>Some prostate cancers might be slow-growing and can be monitored over time whereas others need to be treated right away. To determine how aggressive someone&#8217;s cancer is, doctors look for abnormalities in slices of biopsied tissue on a slide. But this 2D method makes it hard to properly diagnose borderline cases.</p>
<p>Now a team led by the University of Washington has developed a new, non-destructive method that images entire 3D biopsies instead of just a slice. In a proof-of-principle experiment, the researchers imaged 300 3D biopsies taken from 50 patients — six biopsies per patient — and had a computer use 3D and 2D results to predict the likelihood that a patient had aggressive cancer. The 3D features made it easier for the computer to identify the cases that were more likely to recur within five years.</p>
<p>The team <a href="https://cancerres.aacrjournals.org/content/early/2021/11/30/0008-5472.CAN-21-2843">published these results</a> Dec. 1 in Cancer Research.</p>
<p>&#8220;We show for the first time that compared to traditional pathology — where a small fraction of each biopsy is examined in 2D on microscope slides — the ability to examine 100% of a biopsy in 3D is more informative and accurate,&#8221; said senior author <a href="https://www.me.washington.edu/facultyfinder/jonathan-t-c-liu">Jonathan Liu</a>, a UW professor of mechanical engineering and of bioengineering. &#8220;This is exciting because it is the first of hopefully many clinical studies that will demonstrate the value of non-destructive 3D pathology for clinical decision-making, such as determining which patients require aggressive treatments or which subsets of patients would respond best to certain drugs.&#8221;</p>
<p>The researchers used prostate specimens from patients who underwent surgery more than 10 years ago, so the team knew each patient&#8217;s outcome and could use that information to train a computer to predict those outcomes. In this study, half of the samples contained a more aggressive cancer.</p>
<p>To create 3D samples, the researchers extracted “biopsy cores” — cylindrically shaped plugs of tissue — from surgically removed prostates and then stained the biopsy cores to mimic the typical staining used in the 2D method. Then the team imaged each entire biopsy core using an <a href="https://www.washington.edu/news/2017/06/26/microscope-can-scan-tumors-during-surgery-and-examine-cancer-biopsies-in-3-d/">open-top light-sheet microscope</a>, which uses a sheet of light to optically “slice” through and image a tissue sample without destroying it.</p>
<p>The 3D images provided more information than a 2D image — specifically, details about the complex tree-like structure of the glands throughout the tissue. These additional features increased the likelihood that the computer would correctly predict a cancer&#8217;s aggressiveness.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400"><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/y9J92HNPB9s?rel=0" width="100%" height="422" style="border:0"></iframe></span></p>
<p style="font-size: .8em;margin: 0px 0 25.5px;line-height: 1.4em"><strong>Shown here is a video of a volume rendering of glands in two 3D biopsy samples from prostates (yellow: the outer walls of the gland; red: the fluid-filled space inside the gland; purple: what researchers called the &#8220;gland skeleton,&#8221; a stick-like model of the fluid-filled spaces inside the glands). The cancer sample (top) shows smaller and more densely packed glands compared to the benign tissue sample (bottom). <em>Credit: Xie et al./Cancer Research</em></strong></p>
<p>The researchers used new AI methods, including deep-learning image transformation techniques, to help manage and interpret the large datasets this project generated.</p>
<p>&#8220;Over the past decade or so, our lab has focused primarily on building optical imaging devices, including microscopes, for various clinical applications. However, we started to encounter the next big challenge toward clinical adoption: how to manage and interpret the massive datasets that we were acquiring from patient specimens,&#8221; Liu said. &#8220;This paper represents the first study in our lab to develop a novel computational pipeline to analyze our feature-rich datasets. As we continue to refine our imaging technologies and computational analysis methods, and as we perform larger clinical studies, we hope we can help transform the field of pathology to benefit many types of patients.&#8221;</p>
<p>The lead author on this paper is <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/weisi-xie-44a2b512a/">Weisi Xie</a>, a UW mechanical engineering doctoral student. Other co-authors on this paper are <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/robert-serafin-110571bb/">Robert Serafin</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gan-gao-a7771218a/">Gan Gao</a>, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/lindsey-barner-b21b14a9/">Lindsey Barner</a>, all UW mechanical engineering doctoral students; <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/kevin-bishop-b31624b4/">Kevin Bishop</a>, a UW bioengineering doctoral student; <a href="https://dlmp.uw.edu/faculty/reder">Nicholas Reder</a>, a clinical instructor in the laboratory medicine and pathology department in the UW School of Medicine; Hongyi Huang, UW research staff in mechanical engineering; <a href="https://sites.google.com/a/uw.edu/the-vaughan-group/group/chenyi-mao">Chenyi Mao</a>, a UW doctoral student in the chemistry department; <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nadia-postupna-09232b49/">Nadia Postupna</a>, a research scientist in the laboratory medicine and pathology department in the UW School of Medicine; <a href="https://www.me.washington.edu/facultyfinder/soyoung-kang">Soyoung Kang</a>, a UW assistant teaching professor in the mechanical engineering department; Qinghua Han, a UW undergraduate student studying bioengineering; <a href="https://www.washington.edu/urology/people/wright/">Jonathan Wright</a><u>,</u> a professor in the urology department in the UW School of Medicine; <a href="https://dlmp.uw.edu/faculty/keene">C. Dirk Keene</a> and <a href="https://dlmp.uw.edu/faculty/true">Lawrence True</a>, both professors in the laboratory medicine and pathology department in the UW School of Medicine; <a href="https://chem.washington.edu/people/joshua-c-vaughan">Joshua Vaughan</a>, a UW associate professor of chemistry; <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/adamkglaser/">Adam Glaser</a>, a senior scientist at the Allen Institute who completed this research as a UW mechanical engineering postdoctoral researcher; <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/canfkoyuncu/">Can Koyuncu</a>, <a href="https://case.edu/medicine/pqhs/about/people/primary-faculty/pingfu-fu">Pingfu Fu</a>, <a href="https://case.edu/cancer/members/member-directory/andrew-janowczyk">Andrew Janowczyk</a> and <a href="https://case.edu/medicine/ccir/faculty/anant-madabhushi">Anant Madabhushi</a>, all at Case Western Reserve University; <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/patrick-leo-354a70108/">Patrick Leo</a> at Genentech, who completed this research as a doctoral student at Case Western Reserve University; and Sarah Hawley at the Canary Foundation.</p>
<p>This research was funded by the Department of Defense Prostate Cancer Research Program; the National Cancer Institute; the National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute; the National Institute of Biomedical Imaging and Bioengineering; the National Institute of Mental Health; the VA Merit Review Award; the National Science Foundation; the Nancy and Buster Alvord Endowment; and the Prostate Cancer Foundation Young Investigator Award.</p>
<p>Nicholas Reder, Adam Glaser, Lawrence True and Jonathan Liu are co-founders and shareholders of the UW spinout <a href="https://www.lightspeedbio.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Lightspeed Microscopy Inc.</a> This company has licensed the technology used in this paper.</p>
<p>For more information, contact Liu at <a href="mailto:jonliu@uw.edu">jonliu@uw.edu</a>.</p>
<p>Grant numbers: W81XWH-18-10358, W81XWH-19-1-0589, W81XWH-15-1-0558, W81XWH-20-1-0851, K99 CA24068, R01CA244170, U24CA199374, R01CA249992, R01CA202752, R01CA208236, R01CA216579, R01CA220581, R01CA257612, U01CA239055, U01CA248226, U54CA254566, R01HL151277, R01EB031002, R43EB028736, R01MH115767, IBX004121A, 1934292 HDR: I-DIRSE-FW, DGE-1762114, DGE-1762114</p>
<p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F12%2F09%2F3d-imaging-method-may-help-doctors-better-determine-prostate-cancer-aggressiveness%2F&amp;linkname=3D%20imaging%20method%20may%20help%20doctors%20better%20determine%20prostate%20cancer%20aggressiveness" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_twitter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/twitter?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F12%2F09%2F3d-imaging-method-may-help-doctors-better-determine-prostate-cancer-aggressiveness%2F&amp;linkname=3D%20imaging%20method%20may%20help%20doctors%20better%20determine%20prostate%20cancer%20aggressiveness" title="Twitter" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_reddit a2a_counter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/reddit?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F12%2F09%2F3d-imaging-method-may-help-doctors-better-determine-prostate-cancer-aggressiveness%2F&amp;linkname=3D%20imaging%20method%20may%20help%20doctors%20better%20determine%20prostate%20cancer%20aggressiveness" title="Reddit" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F12%2F09%2F3d-imaging-method-may-help-doctors-better-determine-prostate-cancer-aggressiveness%2F&amp;linkname=3D%20imaging%20method%20may%20help%20doctors%20better%20determine%20prostate%20cancer%20aggressiveness" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_print" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/print?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F12%2F09%2F3d-imaging-method-may-help-doctors-better-determine-prostate-cancer-aggressiveness%2F&amp;linkname=3D%20imaging%20method%20may%20help%20doctors%20better%20determine%20prostate%20cancer%20aggressiveness" title="Print" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F12%2F09%2F3d-imaging-method-may-help-doctors-better-determine-prostate-cancer-aggressiveness%2F&#038;title=3D%20imaging%20method%20may%20help%20doctors%20better%20determine%20prostate%20cancer%20aggressiveness" data-a2a-url="https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/12/09/3d-imaging-method-may-help-doctors-better-determine-prostate-cancer-aggressiveness/" data-a2a-title="3D imaging method may help doctors better determine prostate cancer aggressiveness"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<enclosure url="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2017/06/04140821/UW-light-sheet-leads-150x150.jpg" length="8954" type="image/jpeg" />	</item>
		<item>
		<title>A chatbot can help doctors better understand incoming emergency department patients&#8217; social needs</title>
		<link>https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/11/17/chatbot-help-doctors-understand-incoming-emergency-department-patients-social-needs/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sarah McQuate]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2021 18:38:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health and medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Population Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Technology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[UW News blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[College of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Emergency Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Human Centered Design & Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gary Hsieh]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Herbert Duber]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[population health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Raina Langevin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.washington.edu/news/?p=76564</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A team led by the UW developed a chatbot that could ask emergency department visitors about social needs, including housing, food, access to medical care and physical safety. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_76566" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="width: 760px"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full-content wp-image-76566" src="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/11/16151859/greg-rosenke-65stNyETOU0-unsplash_crop-750x500.jpg" alt="A row of green chairs in a waiting room" width="750" height="500" srcset="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/11/16151859/greg-rosenke-65stNyETOU0-unsplash_crop-750x500.jpg 750w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/11/16151859/greg-rosenke-65stNyETOU0-unsplash_crop-300x200.jpg 300w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/11/16151859/greg-rosenke-65stNyETOU0-unsplash_crop-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/11/16151859/greg-rosenke-65stNyETOU0-unsplash_crop-375x250.jpg 375w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/11/16151859/greg-rosenke-65stNyETOU0-unsplash_crop-1140x760.jpg 1140w" sizes="(max-width: 750px) 100vw, 750px" /></p>
<p class="wp-caption-text">A team led by the University of Washington developed a chatbot that could ask emergency department visitors about social needs, including housing, food, access to medical care and physical safety.<a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/65stNyETOU0"><span class="wp-media-credit">Greg Rosenke/Unsplash</span></a></span></p>
</div>
<p>Americans visit hospital emergency departments nearly <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/fastats/emergency-department.htm">130 million times per year</a>. Although the focus of these visits is to address acute illness and injury, doctors are increasingly finding that social needs — such as food and housing insecurity — place many patients at higher risk of getting sick and requiring emergency care.</p>
<p>In order to better serve patients and possibly prevent future emergency department visits, doctors need a way to assess incoming patients to establish a wider context behind their visit.</p>
<p>A team led by the University of Washington developed a chatbot that could ask emergency department visitors about social needs, including housing, food, access to medical care and physical safety. The team tested it on 41 patients in Seattle and Los Angeles emergency departments. Results show that two groups of patients preferred the chatbot: patients who had less than a middle school level of health literacy and patients who appreciated establishing emotional connections.</p>
<p>The team <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/3469595.3469599">presented these results</a> in July at the Conference for Conversational User Interfaces 2021.</p>
<p>&#8220;A few years ago there was a huge buzz around chatbots, and then people started realizing that maybe they aren&#8217;t meant for everything,&#8221; said co-senior author <a href="https://www.hcde.washington.edu/hsieh">Gary Hsieh</a>, a UW associate professor in the human centered design and engineering department. &#8220;We have been trying to figure out opportunities where having a chatbot would actually be meaningful and make sense.&#8221;</p>
<p>One good opportunity involved collaborating with emergency department doctors.</p>
<p>&#8220;We want to understand the upstream issues that bring people into the emergency department. What are the social needs of the patients that we serve and how can we develop interventions that address these needs?&#8221; said co-author Dr. <a href="https://www.uwmedicine.org/bios/herbert-duber#about-tab">Herbert Duber</a>, associate professor of emergency medicine in the UW School of Medicine. &#8220;For many people, including those with low literacy levels, a chatbot makes so much sense for collecting this information.&#8221;</p>
<p>The team designed a chatbot named HarborBot, after the hospitals where it was tested. HarborBot takes patients through a social needs survey that was developed by the Los Angeles County Health Agency. This survey asks patients 36 questions related to demographics, finances, employment, education, housing, food and utilities. It also asks questions related to physical safety, legal needs and access to care.</p>
<p>HarborBot is displayed on a tablet as a typical chat window with the patient&#8217;s and bot&#8217;s conversation showing up in different colored bubbles. HarborBot&#8217;s chat bubble shows animated ellipses when the bot is &#8220;typing.&#8221;</p>
<p>Based on <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7153089/">a previous study</a>, the researchers improved the chatbot’s efficiency and social skills.</p>
<p>For efficiency, the researchers:</p>
<ul>
<li>modified the amount of time the bot looked like it was typing to match the length of text the bot displayed. This means that the bot would &#8220;type&#8221; for a shorter amount of time for a shorter response</li>
<li>added a question at the beginning of the interaction that would allow patients to stop HarborBot from reading all of its questions and responses aloud</li>
<li>placed the patients&#8217; answer options in the same part of the screen so that patients, who were often tired or in pain, could respond without having to move their hands</li>
</ul>
<p>To increase the empathy of the interaction, the team changed the bot&#8217;s reactions to better match the content of the questions and patient responses.</p>
<p>&#8220;Some of the questions are quite sensitive — there are questions about violence and sexual abuse — and the bot&#8217;s original responses said &#8216;Sure,&#8217; &#8216;Great&#8217; or &#8216;Thanks for sharing with us,'&#8221; said lead author <a href="https://rkocielnik.com/">Rafał Kocielnik</a>, who completed this project as a doctoral student at the UW and is now a postdoctoral fellow at Caltech. &#8220;We tried tailoring its responses in a way that made them more appropriate for the content and specific to the patients&#8217; responses, such as &#8216;That must be stressful, thank you for letting me know.'&#8221;</p>
<div id="attachment_76565" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="width: 760px"><a href="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/11/16151853/Fig1_CUI_chatbot_v2.png"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full-content wp-image-76565" src="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/11/16151853/Fig1_CUI_chatbot_v2-750x356.png" alt="Three examples side by side all showing the question &quot;Do you have enough resources to pay for the very basics like food, housing, and medical care?&quot; The web form (on the left) has two options to click: yes or no. The original chatbot (in the middle) shows a conversation between the chatbot and a participant where the participant has answered &quot;no&quot; and the chatbot responds with &quot;got it&quot; and then goes on to the next question: &quot;Do you have any significant outstanding bills or debts?&quot; The improved chatbot (on the right) is having the same conversation except the chatbot's response is &quot;That must be stressful, thank you for letting me know.&quot;" width="750" height="356" srcset="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/11/16151853/Fig1_CUI_chatbot_v2-750x356.png 750w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/11/16151853/Fig1_CUI_chatbot_v2-300x143.png 300w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/11/16151853/Fig1_CUI_chatbot_v2-1024x487.png 1024w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/11/16151853/Fig1_CUI_chatbot_v2-375x178.png 375w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/11/16151853/Fig1_CUI_chatbot_v2-1140x542.png 1140w" sizes="(max-width: 750px) 100vw, 750px" /></a></p>
<p class="wp-caption-text">Shown here is a question from the social needs survey as a form (left), in the original chatbot (middle) and in the improved chatbot (right). The improvements are shown here as a) through e). a) The chatbot asked people if they wanted to continue hearing it read questions out loud. b) If they said no, the chatbot gave them an option to turn it back on later. c) The chatbot varied the amount of time it spent &#8220;typing&#8221; based on the length of its response. d) The team fixed the patient response area to one place on the screen. e) The chatbot&#8217;s responses were more specific to the context of the questions and the patient&#8217;s answers.<span class="wp-media-credit">University of Washington</span></span></p>
</div>
<p>After HarborBot received its upgrades, the researchers tested it at two emergency departments: one at Harborview Medical Center in Seattle and the other at the Harbor-UCLA Medical Center in Los Angeles.</p>
<p>For both locations, the researchers worked at night (between 8 p.m. and 1 a.m. in Seattle and between 4 p.m. and 4 a.m. in Los Angeles). The teams collaborated with triage nurses to select potential participants. Then the researchers took participants to a visitor room where they could still hear announcements. After the patients signed a consent form, they completed:</p>
<ul>
<li>two surveys to gauge health literacy. One survey asks patients to pronounce health-related terms and the other asks patients to <a href="https://www.pfizer.com/health/literacy/public-policy-researchers/nvs-toolkit">answer questions about the nutritional facts label on a pint of ice cream</a></li>
<li>the social needs survey as both a web form through SurveyGizmo and an interaction with HarborBot. These were given in a randomized order</li>
<li>evaluations for both the web form and HarborBot</li>
<li>a survey to gauge a patient&#8217;s desire for emotional interactions</li>
</ul>
<p>At the end, the researchers interviewed the participants about the experience.</p>
<p>The team was not surprised to find that many people with low health literacy preferred the HarborBot version of the survey — 17 out of 20 low-literacy participants chose HarborBot, compared to 8 out of 21 high-literacy participants. People who valued emotional connection also liked the chatbot but these two groups didn&#8217;t necessarily overlap.</p>
<p>&#8220;We thought maybe people with low health literacy would also be more in need of emotional interaction,&#8221; Kocielnik said. &#8220;But it turns out, the two groups are not strongly correlated.&#8221;</p>
<p>For the 23 participants who scored high on the emotional interactions questionnaire, 18 chose HarborBot. Meanwhile only 7 of the 18 participants who scored lower on that questionnaire preferred HarborBot.</p>
<div class="info-box">This paper <a href="https://www.hcde.washington.edu/news/cui-2021" target="_blank" rel="noopener">received an honorable mention award</a> at the 2021 Conference for Conversational User Interfaces.</div>
<p>&#8220;It&#8217;s important to understand that chatbots can benefit people in different ways,&#8221; said co-author <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/rainalangevin/">Raina Langevin</a>, a UW doctoral student in human centered design and engineering.</p>
<p>In the future, the team plans to design a survey system that could tailor the experience to each user. For example, it could start out as the chatbot, but then based on how a user is answering the questions, it could shift into more of a survey format.</p>
<p>&#8220;Our vision would be some sort of kiosk people could use while they are waiting. Or even a QR code that people can scan with their own devices and then answer these questions,&#8221; Hsieh said. &#8220;Ultimately we want to connect people entering emergency departments as smoothly as possible with the resources that they need.&#8221;</p>
<p><a href="http://bime.uw.edu/faculty/andrea-hartzler/">Andrea Hartzler</a> in the UW biomedical and health informatics department is the other co-senior author on this paper. Additional co-authors are Dr. <a href="https://em.uw.edu/faculty/callan-fockele-md">Callan Fockele</a> and Layla Anderson, both in the UW emergency medicine department; Amelia Wang and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/alexargyle/">Alexander Argyle</a>, both of whom completed this research as a UW undergraduate students majoring in human centered design and engineering; Darwin Jones, who completed this research as a UW undergraduate student majoring in biomedical and health informatics; <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jscottgeorge/">James George</a>, Shota Akenaga and Dr. Kabir Yadav at the Harbor-UCLA Medical Center; and Dr. <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/dennis-hsieh-931b123/">Dennis Hsieh</a> at Contra Costa Health Plan. This research was funded by the National Institutes of Health.</p>
<p>For more information, contact Kocielnik at <a href="mailto:rafalko@caltech.edu">rafalko@caltech.edu</a>, Langevin at <a href="mailto:rlangevi@uw.edu">rlangevi@uw.edu</a> and Hsieh at <a href="mailto:garyhs@uw.edu">garyhs@uw.edu</a>. To speak to Herbert Duber, please contact Susan Gregg at <a href="mailto:sghanson@uw.edu">sghanson@uw.edu</a>.</p>
<p>Grant number: UL1 TR002319</p>
<p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F11%2F17%2Fchatbot-help-doctors-understand-incoming-emergency-department-patients-social-needs%2F&amp;linkname=A%20chatbot%20can%20help%20doctors%20better%20understand%20incoming%20emergency%20department%20patients%E2%80%99%20social%20needs" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_twitter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/twitter?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F11%2F17%2Fchatbot-help-doctors-understand-incoming-emergency-department-patients-social-needs%2F&amp;linkname=A%20chatbot%20can%20help%20doctors%20better%20understand%20incoming%20emergency%20department%20patients%E2%80%99%20social%20needs" title="Twitter" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_reddit a2a_counter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/reddit?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F11%2F17%2Fchatbot-help-doctors-understand-incoming-emergency-department-patients-social-needs%2F&amp;linkname=A%20chatbot%20can%20help%20doctors%20better%20understand%20incoming%20emergency%20department%20patients%E2%80%99%20social%20needs" title="Reddit" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F11%2F17%2Fchatbot-help-doctors-understand-incoming-emergency-department-patients-social-needs%2F&amp;linkname=A%20chatbot%20can%20help%20doctors%20better%20understand%20incoming%20emergency%20department%20patients%E2%80%99%20social%20needs" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_print" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/print?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F11%2F17%2Fchatbot-help-doctors-understand-incoming-emergency-department-patients-social-needs%2F&amp;linkname=A%20chatbot%20can%20help%20doctors%20better%20understand%20incoming%20emergency%20department%20patients%E2%80%99%20social%20needs" title="Print" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F11%2F17%2Fchatbot-help-doctors-understand-incoming-emergency-department-patients-social-needs%2F&#038;title=A%20chatbot%20can%20help%20doctors%20better%20understand%20incoming%20emergency%20department%20patients%E2%80%99%20social%20needs" data-a2a-url="https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/11/17/chatbot-help-doctors-understand-incoming-emergency-department-patients-social-needs/" data-a2a-title="A chatbot can help doctors better understand incoming emergency department patients’ social needs"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<enclosure url="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/11/16151859/greg-rosenke-65stNyETOU0-unsplash_crop-150x150.jpg" length="6193" type="image/jpeg" />	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Countermarketing based on anti-smoking campaigns reduces buying of sugary ‘fruit’ drinks for children</title>
		<link>https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/10/28/countermarketing-based-on-anti-smoking-campaigns-reduces-buying-of-sugary-fruit-drinks-for-children/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jake Ellison]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 20:03:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Health and medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interactive]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Population Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Public Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health Systems and Population Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jim Krieger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lina Pinero Walkinshaw]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Public Health]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.washington.edu/news/?p=76242</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Public health messages such as in the image below — designed to reduce parents’ purchases of sugar-sweetened beverages marketed as fruit drinks for children — convinced a significant percentage of parents to avoid those drinks, according to a study by researchers at the University of Washington and the University of Pennsylvania. The UW-led study set...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Public health messages such as in the image below — designed to reduce parents’ purchases of sugar-sweetened beverages marketed as fruit drinks for children — convinced a significant percentage of parents to avoid those drinks, according to a <a href="https://ajph.aphapublications.org/doi/10.2105/AJPH.2021.306488">study</a> by researchers at the University of Washington and the University of Pennsylvania.</p>
<div id="attachment_76251" class="wp-caption alignright" style="width: 385px"><img loading="lazy" class="size-half wp-image-76251" src="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/25132732/kids-rotting-teeth-square-375x391.jpg" alt="image of a child with rotted teeth with text &quot;Sugary fruit drinks are 'naturally' rotting your kid's teeth&quot;" width="375" height="391" srcset="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/25132732/kids-rotting-teeth-square-375x391.jpg 375w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/25132732/kids-rotting-teeth-square-288x300.jpg 288w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/25132732/kids-rotting-teeth-square.jpg 467w" sizes="(max-width: 375px) 100vw, 375px" /></p>
<p class="wp-caption-text">This is an example of a message designed to reduce parents’ spending on sugary beverages. Go to <a href="https://www.truthaboutfruitdrinks.com/">Truth About Fruit Drinks</a> for more countermarketing images and content to share on social media or anywhere.</span></p>
</div>
<p>The UW-led study set out to assess the effect of culturally tailored countermarketing messages on drink choices, similar to stark anti-smoking campaigns, and involved more than 1,600 Latinx parents who participated by joining Facebook groups. Study authors focused on this demographic because Latinx children have a <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/oby.22056">high rate of sugary drink consumption</a>, and the beverage industry <a href="https://media.ruddcenter.uconn.edu/PDFs/ajph_2019_Harris.pdf">intentionally targets the Latinx community</a>, said Dr. <a href="https://depts.washington.edu/hserv/faculty/Krieger_James">James Krieger</a>, lead author and clinical professor of health systems and population health in the UW School of Public Health.</p>
<p>“The negative health effects associated with the consumption of sugary drinks — such as tooth decay or, later in life, diabetes — are disproportionately affecting this community,” Krieger said. “We want these and other kids to be able to avoid developing strong taste preferences for a product that’s ultimately going to harm them.”</p>
<p>To design their study, <a href="https://ajph.aphapublications.org/doi/10.2105/AJPH.2021.306488">published Thursday in the American Journal of Public Health</a>, researchers consulted focus groups involving dozens of Latinx parents from across the country to get their perceptions of how marketing works, how they think about what they are buying for their children, as well as how to culturally tailor messages that would resonate in their community.</p>
<h5></h5>
<div class="info-box">
<h5>Sugary Drink Countermarketing Toolkit</h5>
<p><a href="https://www.truthaboutfruitdrinks.com">Download messages and images for sharing the truth about fruit drinks.</a></p>
</div>
<p>“They know that targeted marketing happens all the time in the digital era, but what really got them was the fact that they were given deceptive information that they felt was leading them to make unhealthy choices on behalf of their kids,” Krieger said.</p>
<p>That industry marketing, Krieger added, led parents to believe fruit drinks are healthy beverages by creating a “halo of health” around the product. Ads, labels, and even online games and cartoons often contain claims about nutrients such as vitamin C and images of healthy kids drinking their products while participating in sports.</p>
<p>With information from those focus groups and the aid of a Latinx marketing firm, the researchers created countermarketing graphics and messages in Spanish and English designed to elicit outrage, fear of the harmful effects on children and other negative emotions. The messages called out specific brands and images, along with describing the adverse effects of these products.</p>
<p>“We looked at anti-tobacco messages and the words and types of images they used,” Krieger said. “We wanted messages that would appeal to folks on an emotional level as well as a cognitive one, because that’s what research shows drives people to make choices.”</p>
<p>The researchers then enrolled 1,628 Latinx parents — predominantly female and from lower-income households — to participate in Facebook groups for six weeks to study the impact of countermessages on those parents’ beverage choices and fruit drink perceptions.</p>
<h2>Sample messages</h2>
<div class="box-outer">
<div class="box three box-left">
<div class="tile">
<div><img loading="lazy" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-76253" src="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/25133939/message1A.jpg" alt="child drinking a juice drink with text &quot;THink again, it's not fruit in this drink, it's fat!&quot;" width="560" height="589" srcset="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/25133939/message1A.jpg 560w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/25133939/message1A-285x300.jpg 285w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/25133939/message1A-375x394.jpg 375w" sizes="(max-width: 560px) 100vw, 560px" /></div>
<p>Message text: <em>Your body turns sugar you drink into fat which can result in diabetes.</em> </p>
</div>
<div class="tile">
<div><img loading="lazy" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-76254" src="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/25134113/message2A.jpg" alt="image of a juice drink with text &quot;The 'all natural fruit drink?'&quot;" width="311" height="311" srcset="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/25134113/message2A.jpg 311w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/25134113/message2A-150x150.jpg 150w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/25134113/message2A-300x300.jpg 300w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/25134113/message2A-50x50.jpg 50w" sizes="(max-width: 311px) 100vw, 311px" /></div>
<p>Message text: <em>WARNING: Calling it natural does not make it good for your kids.</em> </p>
</div>
<div class="tile">
<div><img loading="lazy" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-76255" src="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/25134232/message3A.jpg" alt="Child with a bike helmet drinking water with text &quot;parents! the choice is clear, H2O is the way to go!&quot;" width="500" height="525" srcset="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/25134232/message3A.jpg 500w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/25134232/message3A-286x300.jpg 286w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/25134232/message3A-375x394.jpg 375w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></div>
<p>Message text: <em>Activate your kid’s health by giving them thirst quenching water instead of sugary fruit drinks. The choice is clear.</em></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The study divided parents into three groups. The two “intervention” groups were those who received fruit drink countermessages only, and those receiving a combination of countermessages plus water promotion messages. The third group, the control group, saw safety messages about car seats. Using a simulated online store that offered fruit drinks, soda, water, milk or 100% fruit juice, parents from all three groups chose a drink for their kids and received money they could use to buy the drink in a real store.</p>
<p>The researchers found that parents who saw countermarketing messages alone or combined with pro-water messages were less likely to buy a fruit drink and more likely to buy water. Specifically, parents in the fruit-drink countermarketing group decreased their virtual purchases of these drinks by 31% compared to the control group, and by 43% by the group receiving the combined messages. Parents in the combination group did choose water more often than the first group.</p>
<p><iframe src="https://tableau.washington.edu/views/Fruitdrinksandwater/Studyresults?:embed=y&#038;:showVizHome=no&#038;:host_url=https%3A%2F%2Ftableau.washington.edu%2F&#038;:embed_code_version=3&#038;:tabs=no&#038;:toolbar=no&#038;:showAppBanner=false&#038;:display_count=n&#038;:origin=viz_share_link&#038;:isGuestRedirectFromVizportal=y&#038;:display_spinner=no&#038;:loadOrderID=0&#038;:increment_view_count=no" width="100%" height="627" style="border:0"></iframe></p>
<p>Based on those choices, the authors estimated that children in the combination group consumed 22% less added sugar than the average for children two- to five-years-old. In exit surveys, the authors wrote, the parents in both intervention groups were also “significantly” less likely to trust fruit drink brands.</p>
<p>The researchers said the study is the first to “demonstrate the efficacy of countermessages delivered solely via social media as well as the first to specifically target sweetened beverage consumption among young children.” As a result of this study, the researchers have also created <a href="https://www.truthaboutfruitdrinks.com">a social media countermarketing toolkit</a> for use by anyone to campaign against fruit drink purchases for children.</p>
<p>As executive director of <a href="https://www.healthyfoodamerica.org/">Healthy Food America</a> and with an extensive background in the development and evaluation of community-based chronic disease prevention programs, including a stint with Public Health-Seattle &amp; King County, Krieger hopes the study will be used widely to curb consumption of sugary fruit drinks.</p>
<p>“For me, there’s no point in doing a study if it is not going to be applied to changing things in the world, so we’ve formed an advisory group and created the toolkit and a plan to reach out to national organizations and encourage them to use the messages,” Krieger said.</p>
<p>Co-authors include Taehoon Kwon, who worked on the study while a UW graduate student in economics; Rudy Ruiz, of Interlex, a multicultural advocacy marketing agency in San Antonio; <a href="https://nutr.uw.edu/person/lina-pinero-walkinshaw/">Lina Pinero Walkinshaw</a>, a clinical instructor in the UW School of Public Health; and Jiali Yan and Christina Roberto at the University of Pennsylvania. This research was funded by the Healthy Eating Research Program of the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation; and the Arcora Foundation, the foundation of Delta Dental of Washington.</p>
<p>###</p>
<p>For more information, contact Dr. Krieger at <a href="mailto:jwkrieg@uw.edu">jwkrieg@uw.edu</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<enclosure url="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/02122849/myriam-zilles-tEJm9fvlju8-unsplash-150x150.jpg" length="5921" type="image/jpeg" />	</item>
		<item>
		<title>UW joins USAID’s $125M project to detect emerging viruses with pandemic potential</title>
		<link>https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/10/05/uw-joins-usaids-125-million-project-to-detect-emerging-viruses-with-pandemic-potential/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jake Ellison]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 20:43:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Health and medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Population Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Public Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Alex Greninger]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Alliance for Pandemic Preparedness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Environmental & Occupational Health Sciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Epidemiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Global Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International Training and Education Center for Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Judith Wasserheit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Peter Rabinowitz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[population health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.washington.edu/news/?p=76099</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[To better identify and prevent future pandemics, the University of Washington has become a partner in a five-year global, collaborative agreement with the U.S. Agency for International Development. The newly launched Discovery &#38; Exploration of Emerging Pathogens &#8211; Viral Zoonoses, or DEEP VZN project, has approximately $125 million in anticipated funding and will be led...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_76103" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="width: 760px"><a href="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/05111613/27862316187_ffcbf4b872_k.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full-content wp-image-76103" src="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/05111613/27862316187_ffcbf4b872_k-750x500.jpg" alt="Showing a bat " width="750" height="500" srcset="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/05111613/27862316187_ffcbf4b872_k-750x500.jpg 750w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/05111613/27862316187_ffcbf4b872_k-300x200.jpg 300w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/05111613/27862316187_ffcbf4b872_k-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/05111613/27862316187_ffcbf4b872_k-375x250.jpg 375w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/05111613/27862316187_ffcbf4b872_k-1140x760.jpg 1140w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/05111613/27862316187_ffcbf4b872_k.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 750px) 100vw, 750px" /></a></p>
<p class="wp-caption-text">USAID DEEP VZN scientists hope to collect over 800,000 samples in the five years of the project, most of which will come from wildlife.<span class="wp-media-credit">USAID/Flickr</span></span></p>
</div>
<p>To better identify and prevent future pandemics, the University of Washington has become a partner in a five-year global, collaborative agreement with the U.S. Agency for International Development. The newly launched Discovery &amp; Exploration of Emerging Pathogens &#8211; Viral Zoonoses, or DEEP VZN project, has approximately $125 million in anticipated funding and will be led by Washington State University.</p>
<p>The effort will build scientific capacity in partner countries to safely detect and characterize viruses which have the potential to spill over from wildlife and domestic animals to human populations.</p>
<p>&#8220;The DEEP VZN project provides an exciting chance to better understand why the world is experiencing more frequent and severe outbreaks of zoonotic infectious diseases transmitted between animals and people,” said Dr. <a href="https://deohs.washington.edu/faculty/peter-rabinowitz">Peter Rabinowitz</a>, a co-principal investigator for USAID DEEP VZN and professor of environmental and occupational health sciences in the UW School of Public Health.</p>
<p>“This means gaining knowledge about new viruses that could cause problems in the future, and the ecosystem changes that appear to be driving the process of viruses jumping between species,” Rabinowitz added. “The hope is that this improved understanding will lead to prevention of future pandemics and more resilient ecosystems.”</p>
<p>Rabinowitz is also director of the <a href="https://deohs.washington.edu/cohr/">UW Center for One Health Research</a> and co-director of the <a href="https://depts.washington.edu/pandemicalliance/">UW Alliance for Pandemic Preparedness</a>.</p>
<div class="info-box">
<h5>For more information</h5>
<p>Check out the USAID&#8217;s <a href="https://www.usaid.gov/news-information/press-releases/oct-5-2021-usaid-announces-new-125-million-project-detect-unknown-viruses">media release</a>.</p>
</div>
<p>The project plans to initially partner with five countries in Africa, Asia and Latin America to help local organizations carry out large-scale animal surveillance programs within their own countries safely and test samples for viruses using their own laboratory facilities. This will avoid the process of having to ship samples to other countries for testing and build an international network of laboratories capable of quickly responding to disease outbreaks.</p>
<p>“Since the vast majority of viruses that ignite pandemics have their origin in nonhuman animals, it is critical that we figure out which of the many new zoonotic viruses that we are now identifying are most likely to jump species into humans, spread easily from person to person and cause severe disease or death,” said Dr. <a href="https://globalhealth.washington.edu/faculty/judith-wasserheit">Judith Wasserheit</a>, a co-principal investigator in the project and chair of the UW Department of Global health.</p>
<p>“The <a href="https://depts.washington.edu/pandemicalliance/">UW Alliance for Pandemic Preparedness</a> focuses on a proactive, integrated systems approach to pandemic preparedness that has brought together internationally recognized leaders in the kinds of laboratory methods that will make it possible for the DEEP VZN team to fully sequence and characterize novel viruses in unprecedented breadth and depth,” said Wasserheit, co-director of the Alliance. “In addition, the Alliance’s approach catalyzed collaborations between these lab-based scientists; One Health leaders working at the interface of human, animal and environmental health; and leaders in Global Health who will work with colleagues in focus countries to identify high-risk locations and subpopulations at the human-animal interface.”</p>
<p>The DEEP VZN project will focus on finding previously unknown pathogens from three viral families that have a large potential for viral spillover from animals to humans: coronaviruses, the family that includes SARS-CoV-2, the virus that causes COVID-19; filoviruses, like Ebola virus; and paramyxoviruses, such as Nipah virus. With 70% of new viral outbreaks in people originating from animals, understanding future threats helps protect the U.S. as well as the partner countries.</p>
<p>The goals are ambitious: to collect over 800,000 samples in the five years of the project, most of which will come from wildlife; then to detect whether known and novel viruses from the target families are present in the samples. When those are found, the researchers will determine their zoonotic potential, or the ability to be transmitted between animals and humans.</p>
<p>This process is expected to yield 8,000 to 12,000 novel viruses, which researchers will then screen and genome sequence for the ones that pose the most risk to animal and human health.</p>
<p>The UW Medicine laboratory effort, led by Dr. Alex Greninger, assistant professor of laboratory medicine and pathology at University of Washington School of Medicine, will use the cutting-edge research expertise of five internationally recognized UW Medicine laboratories to develop innovative techniques and provide reference and support activities for virus detection and characterization by in-country labs.</p>
<p>“It’s time to get to work and find some new viruses. We will be building capacity in other countries to be able to find new viruses and characterize them in hopes to better understand coronaviruses and other viruses circulating in the world,” said Greninger.</p>
<p>The UW Medicine labs:</p>
<ul>
<li>The <a href="https://depts.washington.edu/uwvirus/">Greninger Lab</a>will coordinate qRT-PCR and broad serology assay development and in-country training, viral genome recovery and viral glycoprotein characterization.</li>
<li>The David <a href="https://www.bakerlab.org/">Baker Lab</a> will model novel viral glycoproteins to determine risk potential based on in silico screens for potential human receptor affinity.</li>
<li>The David <a href="https://www.veeslerlab.com/">Veesler Lab</a> has detailed mechanisms of viral attachment and entry for novel paramyxoviruses and coronaviruses and will extend these biochemical studies to novel viral glycoproteins discovered in DV.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.galelab.org/">The Michael Gale Jr. Lab </a>will determine the degree and mechanisms of innate immunity evasion in human cells by novel viruses.</li>
<li>The <a href="https://cerid.uw.edu/lab/van-voorhis-lab">Van Voorhis Lab </a>will produce recombinant proteins for in-country serological analysis as it has done for SARS-CoV-2.</li>
</ul>
<p>The UW Department of Global Health will apply its experience in more than 145 countries and expertise in capacity strengthening through the <a href="https://www.washington.edu/research/research-centers/international-training-and-education-center-for-health-i-tech/">International Training and Education Center for Health</a>, or I-TECH, to support sustainable sampling and strengthen in-country laboratory programs.</p>
<p>In addition to UW and WSU, USAID DEEP VZN includes virology expertise of The Washington University at St. Louis, as well as data management and in-country expertise of public health nonprofits PATH, based in Seattle, and FHI 360, based in North Carolina. These partners have extensive established presence and partners in countries in the target regions.</p>
<p>“To make sure the world is better prepared for these infectious disease events, which are likely to happen more frequently as wild areas become increasingly fragmented, we need to be ready,” said Felix Lankester, lead principal investigator for USAID DEEP VZN and associate professor with WSU’s Paul G. Allen School for Global Health. “We will work to not only detect viruses but also build capacity in other countries, so the United States can collaborate with them in carrying out this important work.”</p>
<p>###</p>
<p>For more information, contact Jake Ellison at Jbe3@uw.edu</p>
<p><em>This story was adapted from a Washington State University <a href="https://news.wsu.edu/press-release/2021/10/05/wsu-to-lead-125-million-usaid-project-to-detect-emerging-viruses/">news release</a>. </em></p>
<p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F10%2F05%2Fuw-joins-usaids-125-million-project-to-detect-emerging-viruses-with-pandemic-potential%2F&amp;linkname=UW%20joins%20USAID%E2%80%99s%20%24125M%20project%20to%20detect%20emerging%20viruses%20with%20pandemic%20potential" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_twitter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/twitter?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F10%2F05%2Fuw-joins-usaids-125-million-project-to-detect-emerging-viruses-with-pandemic-potential%2F&amp;linkname=UW%20joins%20USAID%E2%80%99s%20%24125M%20project%20to%20detect%20emerging%20viruses%20with%20pandemic%20potential" title="Twitter" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_reddit a2a_counter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/reddit?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F10%2F05%2Fuw-joins-usaids-125-million-project-to-detect-emerging-viruses-with-pandemic-potential%2F&amp;linkname=UW%20joins%20USAID%E2%80%99s%20%24125M%20project%20to%20detect%20emerging%20viruses%20with%20pandemic%20potential" title="Reddit" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F10%2F05%2Fuw-joins-usaids-125-million-project-to-detect-emerging-viruses-with-pandemic-potential%2F&amp;linkname=UW%20joins%20USAID%E2%80%99s%20%24125M%20project%20to%20detect%20emerging%20viruses%20with%20pandemic%20potential" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_print" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/print?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F10%2F05%2Fuw-joins-usaids-125-million-project-to-detect-emerging-viruses-with-pandemic-potential%2F&amp;linkname=UW%20joins%20USAID%E2%80%99s%20%24125M%20project%20to%20detect%20emerging%20viruses%20with%20pandemic%20potential" title="Print" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F10%2F05%2Fuw-joins-usaids-125-million-project-to-detect-emerging-viruses-with-pandemic-potential%2F&#038;title=UW%20joins%20USAID%E2%80%99s%20%24125M%20project%20to%20detect%20emerging%20viruses%20with%20pandemic%20potential" data-a2a-url="https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/10/05/uw-joins-usaids-125-million-project-to-detect-emerging-viruses-with-pandemic-potential/" data-a2a-title="UW joins USAID’s $125M project to detect emerging viruses with pandemic potential"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<enclosure url="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/10/05111613/27862316187_ffcbf4b872_k-150x150.jpg" length="5962" type="image/jpeg" />	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Video: Arsenic makes these south Puget Sound fish unsafe to eat</title>
		<link>https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/09/23/arsenic-makes-these-south-puget-sound-fish-unsafe-to-eat/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kiyomi Taguchi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 24 Sep 2021 00:59:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health and medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Public Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Soundbites]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[UW and the community]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[College of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Civil & Environmental Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jim Gawel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rebecca Neumann]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[UW Tacoma]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.washington.edu/news/?p=75907</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Researchers at the University of Washington and UW Tacoma have been studying arsenic levels in the mud, water and in creatures from lakes in the south Puget Sound area. Eating contaminated fish or snails from these lakes could lead to health risks.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p class="p2"><span class="s1"><iframe title="Arsenic make these south Puget Sound fish unsafe to eat" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/AYDpwEp-Z3Q?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400">Researchers at the University of Washington and UW Tacoma have been studying arsenic levels in the mud, water and in creatures from lakes in the south Puget Sound area. Eating contaminated fish or snails from these lakes could lead to health risks because of the high arsenic levels found in those organisms.</span></p>
<div class="info-box info-box-large">
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><iframe title="Soundbites &amp; B-roll: Arsenic in south sound lakes and fish" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Vsi9NCp5_-I?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></span></p>
<h4 class="p1"><strong><span class="s1">For journalists: </span></strong></h4>
<p class="p1"><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/19wVHydPcRpIJoaBYCPe5A7dRLj-uO45H/view?usp=sharing" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span class="s1">Download soundbites &amp; B-roll</span></a></p>
</div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400">Pollution from regional smelter emissions is likely the source of high concentrations of arsenic found at the bottom of lakes in King and Pierce counties. Arsenic is a chemical linked to increased cancer risk. </span></p>
<div class="mceTemp"></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400">The researchers found that creatures that live in shallow lakes (such as Bonney, Steel and Killarney) were more likely to have higher levels of arsenic compared to creatures living in deeper lakes (such as Angle Lake) even though Angle Lake and Lake Killarney have similar levels of arsenic on the bottom. The team detected levels associated with increased cancer risk for the following activities: </span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><span style="font-weight: 400">Eating snails from any of the studied lakes for one meal a month</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><span style="font-weight: 400">Eating crayfish from Steel Lake and Lake Killarney for one meal a month</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400"><span style="font-weight: 400"><span style="font-weight: 400">Eating sunfish from Lake Killarney for two meals a month</span></span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400">The team is currently working with the Department of Health and Department of Ecology on actions to protect human health. The researchers are also beginning to work on an affordable and effective way to clean up the lakes. </span></p>
<div id="attachment_75910" class="wp-caption alignright" style="width: 310px"><a href="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/09/23173924/IMG_0943.MOV.00_01_24_11.Still003.png"><img loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-75910" src="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/09/23173924/IMG_0943.MOV.00_01_24_11.Still003-300x169.png" alt="A big mouth bass being held over a tank." width="300" height="169" srcset="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/09/23173924/IMG_0943.MOV.00_01_24_11.Still003-300x169.png 300w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/09/23173924/IMG_0943.MOV.00_01_24_11.Still003-1024x576.png 1024w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/09/23173924/IMG_0943.MOV.00_01_24_11.Still003-375x211.png 375w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/09/23173924/IMG_0943.MOV.00_01_24_11.Still003-750x422.png 750w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/09/23173924/IMG_0943.MOV.00_01_24_11.Still003-1140x641.png 1140w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/09/23173924/IMG_0943.MOV.00_01_24_11.Still003.png 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></p>
<p class="wp-caption-text">Big mouth bass caught in Lake Killarney.<span class="wp-media-credit">Kiyomi Taguchi / University of Wsahington</span></span></p>
</div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400"><a href="https://www.ce.washington.edu/news/article/2021-06-15/food-for-thought">Read more about this research here. </a></span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400">###</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400">For more information, contact </span><a href="https://directory.tacoma.uw.edu/employee/jimgawel"><span style="font-weight: 400">Jim Gawel</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400"> at </span><a href="mailto:jimgawel@uw.edu"><span style="font-weight: 400">jimgawel@uw.edu</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400"> and </span><a href="https://www.ce.washington.edu/facultyfinder/rebecca-b-neumann"><span style="font-weight: 400">Rebecca Neumann</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400"> at </span><a href="mailto:rbneum@uw.edu"><span style="font-weight: 400">rbneum@uw.edu</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400">.</span></p>
<p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F09%2F23%2Farsenic-makes-these-south-puget-sound-fish-unsafe-to-eat%2F&amp;linkname=Video%3A%20Arsenic%20makes%20these%20south%20Puget%20Sound%20fish%20unsafe%20to%20eat" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_twitter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/twitter?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F09%2F23%2Farsenic-makes-these-south-puget-sound-fish-unsafe-to-eat%2F&amp;linkname=Video%3A%20Arsenic%20makes%20these%20south%20Puget%20Sound%20fish%20unsafe%20to%20eat" title="Twitter" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_reddit a2a_counter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/reddit?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F09%2F23%2Farsenic-makes-these-south-puget-sound-fish-unsafe-to-eat%2F&amp;linkname=Video%3A%20Arsenic%20makes%20these%20south%20Puget%20Sound%20fish%20unsafe%20to%20eat" title="Reddit" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F09%2F23%2Farsenic-makes-these-south-puget-sound-fish-unsafe-to-eat%2F&amp;linkname=Video%3A%20Arsenic%20makes%20these%20south%20Puget%20Sound%20fish%20unsafe%20to%20eat" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_print" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/print?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F09%2F23%2Farsenic-makes-these-south-puget-sound-fish-unsafe-to-eat%2F&amp;linkname=Video%3A%20Arsenic%20makes%20these%20south%20Puget%20Sound%20fish%20unsafe%20to%20eat" title="Print" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F09%2F23%2Farsenic-makes-these-south-puget-sound-fish-unsafe-to-eat%2F&#038;title=Video%3A%20Arsenic%20makes%20these%20south%20Puget%20Sound%20fish%20unsafe%20to%20eat" data-a2a-url="https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/09/23/arsenic-makes-these-south-puget-sound-fish-unsafe-to-eat/" data-a2a-title="Video: Arsenic makes these south Puget Sound fish unsafe to eat"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<enclosure url="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/09/23174421/IMG_0943.MOV.00_00_58_07.Still002-150x150.png" length="47943" type="image/png" />      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Sarah McQuate]]></dc:creator>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New analysis of landmark scurvy study leads to update on vitamin C needs</title>
		<link>https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/08/16/new-analysis-of-landmark-scurvy-study-leads-to-update-on-vitamin-c-needs/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jake Ellison]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2021 16:46:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Health and medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Population Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Public Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Epidemiology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Phillipe Hujoel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Dentistry]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.washington.edu/news/?p=75326</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It was wartime and food was scarce. Leaders of England’s effort to wage war and help the public survive during World War II needed to know: Were the rations in lifeboats adequate for survival at sea? And, among several experiments important for public as well as military heath, how much vitamin C did a person...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_75330" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="width: 760px"><a href="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/08/16094311/pasja1000_Pixabay-.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full-content wp-image-75330" src="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/08/16094311/pasja1000_Pixabay--750x500.jpg" alt="" width="750" height="500" srcset="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/08/16094311/pasja1000_Pixabay--750x500.jpg 750w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/08/16094311/pasja1000_Pixabay--300x200.jpg 300w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/08/16094311/pasja1000_Pixabay--1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/08/16094311/pasja1000_Pixabay--375x250.jpg 375w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/08/16094311/pasja1000_Pixabay--1140x760.jpg 1140w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/08/16094311/pasja1000_Pixabay-.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 750px) 100vw, 750px" /></a></p>
<p class="wp-caption-text">Analysis of a landmark vitamin C study confirms: You need at least 100 milligrams of vitamin C a day to stay healthy.<span class="wp-media-credit">pasja1000/Pixabay </span></span></p>
</div>
<p>It was wartime and food was scarce. Leaders of England’s effort to wage war and help the public survive during World War II needed to know: Were the rations in lifeboats adequate for survival at sea? And, among several experiments important for public as well as military heath, how much vitamin C did a person need to avoid the deadly disease scurvy?</p>
<p>In one experiment at the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sorby_Research_Institute">Sorby Research Institute</a> in Sheffield, called the <a href="https://www.sheffield.ac.uk/library/special/sorbyres">“shipwreck” experiment,</a> volunteers were fed only what the navy carried in lifeboats. The grueling experiment resulted in more water and less food being carried in lifeboats.</p>
<p>One of the more robust experiments run on human subjects during this time in England, which has had long-lasting public health consequences, was a <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/services/aop-cambridge-core/content/view/3ECC9D3AFDC4A83DC4FBF48B48721E40/S0029665153000553a.pdf/div-class-title-the-sheffield-experiment-on-the-vitamin-c-requirement-of-human-adults-a-href-fn01-ref-type-fn-a-div.pdf">vitamin C depletion study</a> started in 1944, also at Sorby. This medical experiment involved 20 subjects, most of whom were conscientious objectors living in the building where many experiments, including the shipwreck experiment, were conducted. They were overseen by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hans_Krebs_(biochemist)">a future Nobel Prize winner</a>, and detailed data was kept on each participant in the study.</p>
<p>“The vitamin C experiment is a shocking study,” said <a href="https://dental.washington.edu/people/philippe-p-hujoel/">Philippe Hujoel</a>, lead author of <a href="https://academic.oup.com/ajcn/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/ajcn/nqab262/6352175">a new analysis</a> of the Sorby vitamin C experiment, a practicing dentist and professor of oral health sciences in the UW School of Dentistry. “They depleted people’s vitamin C levels long-term and created life-threatening emergencies. It would never fly now.”</p>
<div class="info-box info-box-large">
<h5>Related UW study:</h5>
<p><a href="https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/01/31/bleeding-gums-may-be-a-sign-you-need-more-vitamin-c-in-your-diet/"><strong>Bleeding gums may be a sign you need more vitamin C in your diet</strong></a></p>
</div>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Even though two trial participants developed life-threatening heart problems because of the vitamin C depletion, Hujoel added, none of the subjects were permanently harmed, and in later interviews several participants said they would volunteer again given the importance of the research.</p>
<p>Because of the war and food shortages, there was not enough vitamin C available, and they wanted to be conservative with the supplies, explained Hujoel, who is also an adjunct professor of epidemiology. The goal of the Sorby investigators was not to determine the required vitamin C intake for optimal health; it was to find out the minimum vitamin C requirements for preventing scurvy.</p>
<p>Vitamin C is an important element in your body’s ability to heal wounds because the creation of scar tissue depends on the collagen protein, and the production of collagen depends on vitamin C. In addition to knitting skin back together, collagen also maintains the integrity of blood vessel walls, thus protecting against stroke and heart disease.</p>
<p>In the Sorby trial, researchers assigned participants to zero, 10 or 70 milligrams a day for an average of nine months. The depleted subjects were then repleted and saturated with vitamin C. Experimental wounds were made during this depletion and repletion. The investigators used the scar strength of experimental wounds as a measure of adequate vitamin C levels since poor wound healing, in addition to such conditions as bleeding gums, are an indication of scurvy.</p>
<p>In the end, the Sorby researchers said 10 milligrams a day was enough to ward off signs of scurvy. Partly based on these findings, the WHO recommends 45 milligrams a day. Hujoel said that the findings of the re-analyses of the Sorby data suggest that the WHO’s recommendation is too low to prevent weak scar strength.</p>
<p>In a bit of scientific detective work, Hujoel said he tracked down and reviewed the study’s data, and with the aid of <a href="https://statgen.hms.harvard.edu/people/margaux-hujoel">Margaux Hujoel</a>, a scientist with Brigham and Women’s Hospital/Harvard Medical School, put the data through modern statistical techniques designed to handle small sample sizes, techniques not available to the original scientists. The results of their work were <a href="https://academic.oup.com/ajcn/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/ajcn/nqab262/6352175">published Monday in the American Journal of Clinical Nutrition</a>.</p>
<p>The Hujoels discovered that the data from this unique study — which has been a cornerstone used by WHO and other agencies for establishing healthy levels of vitamin C in humans — needed more than an “eyeball method” of data assessment.</p>
<p>“It is concluded that the failure to reevaluate the data of a landmark trial with novel statistical methods as they became available may have led to a misleading narrative on the vitamin C needs for the prevention and treatment of collagen-related pathologies,” the researchers wrote.</p>
<p>“Robust parametric analyses of the (Sorby) trial data reveal that an average daily vitamin C intake of 95 mg is required to prevent weak scar strength for 97.5% of the population. Such a vitamin C intake is more than double the daily 45 mg vitamin C intake recommended by the WHO but is consistent with the writing panels for the National Academy of Medicine and (other) countries,” they add.</p>
<p>The Hujoels’ study also found that recovery from a vitamin C deficiency takes a long time and requires higher levels of vitamin C. Even an average daily dose of 90 milligrams a day of vitamin C for six months failed to restore normal scar strength for the depleted study participants.</p>
<p>###</p>
<p>For more information, contact Philippe Hujoel at <a href="mailto:hujoel@uw.edu">hujoel@uw.edu</a>.</p>
<p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F08%2F16%2Fnew-analysis-of-landmark-scurvy-study-leads-to-update-on-vitamin-c-needs%2F&amp;linkname=New%20analysis%20of%20landmark%20scurvy%20study%20leads%20to%20update%20on%20vitamin%20C%20needs" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_twitter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/twitter?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F08%2F16%2Fnew-analysis-of-landmark-scurvy-study-leads-to-update-on-vitamin-c-needs%2F&amp;linkname=New%20analysis%20of%20landmark%20scurvy%20study%20leads%20to%20update%20on%20vitamin%20C%20needs" title="Twitter" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_reddit a2a_counter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/reddit?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F08%2F16%2Fnew-analysis-of-landmark-scurvy-study-leads-to-update-on-vitamin-c-needs%2F&amp;linkname=New%20analysis%20of%20landmark%20scurvy%20study%20leads%20to%20update%20on%20vitamin%20C%20needs" title="Reddit" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F08%2F16%2Fnew-analysis-of-landmark-scurvy-study-leads-to-update-on-vitamin-c-needs%2F&amp;linkname=New%20analysis%20of%20landmark%20scurvy%20study%20leads%20to%20update%20on%20vitamin%20C%20needs" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_print" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/print?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F08%2F16%2Fnew-analysis-of-landmark-scurvy-study-leads-to-update-on-vitamin-c-needs%2F&amp;linkname=New%20analysis%20of%20landmark%20scurvy%20study%20leads%20to%20update%20on%20vitamin%20C%20needs" title="Print" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F08%2F16%2Fnew-analysis-of-landmark-scurvy-study-leads-to-update-on-vitamin-c-needs%2F&#038;title=New%20analysis%20of%20landmark%20scurvy%20study%20leads%20to%20update%20on%20vitamin%20C%20needs" data-a2a-url="https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/08/16/new-analysis-of-landmark-scurvy-study-leads-to-update-on-vitamin-c-needs/" data-a2a-title="New analysis of landmark scurvy study leads to update on vitamin C needs"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<enclosure url="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/08/16094311/pasja1000_Pixabay--150x150.jpg" length="7749" type="image/jpeg" />	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Scientists model &#8216;true prevalence&#8217; of COVID-19 throughout pandemic</title>
		<link>https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/07/26/covid-19-true-prevalence/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[James Urton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2021 19:01:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Health and medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Interactive]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Adrian Raftery]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[College of Arts & Sciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[COVID-19]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[COVID-19 studies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Sociology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Statistics]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.washington.edu/news/?p=75073</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Two University of Washington scientists have developed a statistical framework that incorporates key COVID-19 data — such as case counts and deaths due to COVID-19 — to model the true prevalence of this disease in the United States and individual states. Their approach, published the week of July 26 in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, projects that in the U.S. as many as 60% of COVID-19 cases went undetected as of March 7, 2021, the last date for which the dataset they employed is available.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><iframe src="https://tableau.washington.edu/views/COVID-19prevalencemap/Map?:embed=y&#038;:showVizHome=no&#038;:host_url=https%3A%2F%2Ftableau.washington.edu%2F&#038;:embed_code_version=3&#038;:tabs=no&#038;:toolbar=no&#038;:isGuestRedirectFromVizportal=y&#038;:display_spinner=no&#038;:loadOrderID=0&#038;:increment_view_count=no" width="100%" height="727" style="border:0"></iframe><br />
Government officials and policymakers have tried to use numbers to grasp COVID-19’s impact. Figures like the number of hospitalizations or deaths reflect part of this burden. Each datapoint tells only part of the story. But no one figure describes the true pervasiveness of the novel coronavirus by revealing the number of people actually infected at a given time — an important figure to help scientists understand if herd immunity can be reached, even with vaccinations.</p>
<p>Now, two University of Washington scientists have developed a statistical framework that incorporates key COVID-19 data — such as case counts and deaths due to COVID-19 — to model the true prevalence of this disease in the United States and individual states. Their approach, <a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/118/31/e2103272118" target="_blank" rel="noopener">published online</a> July 26 in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, projects that in the U.S. as many as 60% of COVID-19 cases went undetected as of March 7, 2021, the last date for which the dataset they employed is available.</p>
<p>This framework could help officials determine the true burden of disease in their region — both diagnosed and undiagnosed — and direct resources accordingly, said the researchers.</p>
<div class="info-box">
<h6><strong>Related link</strong></h6>
<p>Dashboard created by Irons and Raftery: “<a href="https://rsc.stat.washington.edu/covid-dashboard/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">COVID Infections in the United States</a>”</p>
</div>
<p>“There are all sorts of different data sources we can draw on to understand the COVID-19 pandemic — the number of hospitalizations in a state, or the number of tests that come back positive. But each source of data has its own flaws that would give a biased picture of what’s really going on,” said senior author <a href="https://soc.washington.edu/people/adrian-raftery" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Adrian Raftery</a>, a UW professor of sociology and of statistics. “What we wanted to do is to develop a framework that corrects the flaws in multiple data sources and draws on their strengths to give us an idea of COVID-19’s prevalence in a region, a state or the country as a whole.”</p>
<p>Data sources can be biased in different ways. For example, one widely cited COVID-19 statistic is the proportion of test results in a region or state that come back positive. But since access to tests, and a willingness to be tested, vary by location, that figure alone cannot provide a clear picture of COVID-19’s prevalence, said Raftery.</p>
<p>Other statistical methods often try to correct the bias in one data source to model the true prevalence of disease in a region. For their approach, Raftery and lead author <a href="https://stat.uw.edu/about-us/people/nicholas-irons" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nicholas Irons</a>, a UW doctoral student in statistics, incorporated three factors: the number of confirmed COVID-19 cases, the number of deaths due to COVID-19 and the number of COVID-19 tests administered each day as reported by the <a href="https://covidtracking.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">COVID Tracking Project</a>. In addition, they incorporated results from random COVID-19 testing of Indiana and Ohio residents as an “anchor” for their method.</p>
<p>The researchers used their framework to model COVID-19 prevalence in the U.S. and each of the states up through March 7, 2021. On that date, according to their framework, an estimated 19.7% of U.S. residents, or about 65 million people, had been infected. This indicates that the U.S. is unlikely to reach herd immunity without its ongoing vaccination campaign, Raftery and Irons said. In addition, the U.S. had an undercount factor of 2.3, the researchers found, which means that only about 1 in 2.3 COVID-19 cases were being confirmed through testing. Put another way, some 60% of cases were not counted at all.</p>
<p>This COVID-19 undercount rate also varied widely by state, and could have multiple causes, according to Irons.</p>
<p>“It can depend on the severity of the pandemic and the amount of testing in that state,” said Irons. “If you have a state with severe pandemic but limited testing, the undercount can be very high, and you’re missing the vast majority of infections that are occurring. Or, you could have a situation where testing is widespread and the pandemic is not as severe. There, the undercount rate would be lower.”</p>
<p>In addition, the undercount factor fluctuated by state or region as the pandemic progressed due to differences in access to medical care among regions, changes in the availability of tests and other factors, Raftery said.</p>
<div class="info-box info-box-large">
<h6><strong>Related coverage</strong></h6>
<p>July 30, 2020: “<a href="https://www.washington.edu/news/2020/07/30/national-academies-covid19-data-guide/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">National Academies publishes guide to help public officials make sense of COVID-19 data</a>”</p>
</div>
<p>With the true prevalence of COVID-19, Raftery and Irons calculated other useful figures for states, such as the infection fatality rate, which is the percentage of infected people who had succumbed to COVID-19, as well as the cumulative incidence, which is the percentage of a state’s population who have had COVID-19.</p>
<p>Ideally, regular random testing of individuals would show the level of infection in a state, region or even nationally, said Raftery. But in the COVID-19 pandemic, only Indiana and Ohio conducted random viral testing of residents, datasets that were critical in helping the researchers develop their framework. In the absence of widespread random testing, this new method could help officials assess the true burden of disease in this pandemic and the next one.</p>
<p>“We think this tool can make a difference by giving the people in charge a more accurate picture of how many people are infected, and what fraction of them are being missed by current testing and treatment efforts,” said Raftery.</p>
<p>The research was funded by the National Institutes of Health.</p>
<p><em>For more information, contact Raftery at <a href="mailto:raftery@uw.edu">raftery@uw.edu</a>.</em></p>
<p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F26%2Fcovid-19-true-prevalence%2F&amp;linkname=Scientists%20model%20%E2%80%98true%20prevalence%E2%80%99%20of%20COVID-19%20throughout%20pandemic" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_twitter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/twitter?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F26%2Fcovid-19-true-prevalence%2F&amp;linkname=Scientists%20model%20%E2%80%98true%20prevalence%E2%80%99%20of%20COVID-19%20throughout%20pandemic" title="Twitter" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_reddit a2a_counter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/reddit?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F26%2Fcovid-19-true-prevalence%2F&amp;linkname=Scientists%20model%20%E2%80%98true%20prevalence%E2%80%99%20of%20COVID-19%20throughout%20pandemic" title="Reddit" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F26%2Fcovid-19-true-prevalence%2F&amp;linkname=Scientists%20model%20%E2%80%98true%20prevalence%E2%80%99%20of%20COVID-19%20throughout%20pandemic" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_print" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/print?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F26%2Fcovid-19-true-prevalence%2F&amp;linkname=Scientists%20model%20%E2%80%98true%20prevalence%E2%80%99%20of%20COVID-19%20throughout%20pandemic" title="Print" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F26%2Fcovid-19-true-prevalence%2F&#038;title=Scientists%20model%20%E2%80%98true%20prevalence%E2%80%99%20of%20COVID-19%20throughout%20pandemic" data-a2a-url="https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/07/26/covid-19-true-prevalence/" data-a2a-title="Scientists model ‘true prevalence’ of COVID-19 throughout pandemic"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<enclosure url="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/07/26102015/map-featured-150x150.jpg" length="5683" type="image/jpeg" />	</item>
		<item>
		<title>20 UW researchers elected to the Washington State Academy of Sciences for 2021</title>
		<link>https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/07/16/wsas-2021/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[James Urton]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2021 22:51:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health and medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Honors and awards]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Population Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[UW News blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Alshakim Nelson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Anna Karlin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brandi Cossairt]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Center for Dialysis Innovation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Center for Emerging and Re-emerging Infectious Diseases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Center for Health and the Global Environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Center for Urban Waters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cheryl Kaiser]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Clean Energy Institute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[College of Arts & Sciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[College of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[College of the Environment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dan Jaffe]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Aeronautics & Astronautics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Anesthesiology and Pain Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Applied Mathematics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Astronomy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Biological Structure]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Biology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Biostatistics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Chemistry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Environmental & Occupational Health Sciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Global Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Ophthalmology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Pediatrics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[eScience Institute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Harborview Injury Prevention & Research Center]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Joel Baker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jonathan Himmelfarb]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Julie Theriot]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kristi Morgansen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kristie Ebi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lisa Graumlich]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Molecular Engineering & Sciences Institute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Monica Vavilala]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Munira Khalil]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Patrick Heagerty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science & Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Puget Sound Institute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rachel Wong]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Randy LeVeque]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sapna Cheryan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Environmental and Forest Sciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Public Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tueng Shen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[UW Bothell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[UW Eye Institute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[UW Tacoma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Victoria Meadows]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Virtual Planetary Laboratory]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Washington State Academy of Sciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wesley Van Voorhis]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.washington.edu/news/?p=74984</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Twenty scientists and engineers at the University of Washington are among the 38 new members elected to the Washington State Academy of Sciences for 2021, according to a July 15 announcement. New members were chosen for “their outstanding record of scientific and technical achievement, and their willingness to work on behalf of the Academy to bring the best available science to bear on issues within the state of Washington.”]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_69538" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="width: 760px"><a href="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2020/07/16150934/20200515_May-Campus-1112-Edit-Edit_web.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full-content wp-image-69538" src="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2020/07/16150934/20200515_May-Campus-1112-Edit-Edit_web-750x500.jpg" alt="" width="750" height="500" srcset="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2020/07/16150934/20200515_May-Campus-1112-Edit-Edit_web-750x500.jpg 750w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2020/07/16150934/20200515_May-Campus-1112-Edit-Edit_web-300x200.jpg 300w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2020/07/16150934/20200515_May-Campus-1112-Edit-Edit_web-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2020/07/16150934/20200515_May-Campus-1112-Edit-Edit_web-375x250.jpg 375w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2020/07/16150934/20200515_May-Campus-1112-Edit-Edit_web-1140x760.jpg 1140w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2020/07/16150934/20200515_May-Campus-1112-Edit-Edit_web.jpg 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 750px) 100vw, 750px" /></a></p>
<p class="wp-caption-text">A spring day on the University of Washington campus.<span class="wp-media-credit">Dennis Wise</span></span></p>
</div>
<p>Twenty scientists and engineers at the University of Washington are among the 38 new members elected to the Washington State Academy of Sciences for 2021, according to a July 15 <a href="https://washacad.org/news-info/38-new-members-elected-to-wsas/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">announcement</a>. New members were chosen for “their outstanding record of scientific and technical achievement, and their willingness to work on behalf of the Academy to bring the best available science to bear on issues within the state of Washington.”</p>
<p>Current academy members selected 29 of the new members. An additional nine were elected by virtue of joining one of the National Academies.</p>
<p>New UW members who were elected by current academy members are:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://directory.tacoma.uw.edu/employee/jebaker" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Joel Baker</a>, professor and Port of Tacoma Chair in Environmental Science at UW Tacoma, director of the <a href="https://www.pugetsoundinstitute.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Puget Sound Institute</a> and science director of the <a href="https://www.urbanwaters.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Center for Urban Waters</a>, “for foundational work on the environmental fate, behavior and toxicity of PCBs.”</li>
<li><a href="https://psych.uw.edu/directory/2373" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sapna Cheryan</a>, professor of psychology, “for contributions in research on racial and gender inequality that has influenced practices in education, government, and business” and “for shifting the explanation for inequality away from individual deficiencies and examining how societal stereotypes and structures cause inequalities.”</li>
<li><a href="https://chem.washington.edu/people/brandi-m-cossairt" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Brandi Cossairt</a>, professor of chemistry and member faculty at the <a href="https://www.cei.washington.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Clean Energy Institute</a>, “for leadership in the innovative synthesis and chemical modification of nanoscale materials for application in light emission and catalysis.”</li>
<li><a href="https://globalhealth.washington.edu/faculty/kristie-ebi" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kristie Ebi</a>, professor of global health and of environmental and occupational health sciences, and founding director of the <a href="https://deohs.washington.edu/change" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Center for Health and the Global Environment</a>, “for work on the health impacts of climate change, on climate impact forecasting, on adaptation to climate change and on climate policy to protect health.”</li>
<li><a href="https://environment.uw.edu/faculty/lisa-graumlich/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Lisa Graumlich</a>, professor of environmental and forest sciences and dean emeritus of the College of the Environment, “for foundational studies of regional paleoenvironmental history and sustained excellence in academic leadership to catalyze and sustain transformative research and educational initiatives.” Graumlich is also <a href="https://www.washington.edu/news/2020/11/18/lisa-graumlich-dean-of-uw-college-of-the-environment-named-president-elect-of-agu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">president-elect of the American Geophysical Union</a>.</li>
<li>Dr. <a href="https://nephrology.uw.edu/faculty/jonathan-himmelfarb-md" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jonathan Himmelfarb</a>, the Joseph W. Eschbach Endowed Chair in Kidney Research and co-director of the <a href="https://cdi.washington.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Center for Dialysis Innovation</a>, “for pioneering contributions and outstanding achievements in the development of the novel wearable artificial kidney, as well as numerous investigator-initiated clinical trials and multi-center collaborative studies.”</li>
<li><a href="https://www.uwb.edu/physical-sciences/faculty/chemistrysci/djaffe" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Daniel Jaffe</a>, professor of environmental chemistry and chair of the Physical Sciences Division at UW Bothell, “for leadership in monitoring and understanding the global transport of atmospheric pollutants from energy production, wildfire, and other sources, as well as science communication and service that has informed citizens and enhanced public policy.”</li>
<li><a href="https://psych.uw.edu/directory/2406" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cheryl Kaiser</a>, professor and chair of psychology, “for contributions demonstrating how psychological science can inform long-standing issues about racial and gender discrimination” and “for research that has deep and penetrating implications for the law and societal efforts to remedy social inequities with evidence-based programs and actions.”</li>
<li><a href="https://chem.washington.edu/people/munira-khalil" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Munira Khalil</a>, the Leon C. Johnson Professor of Chemistry, member faculty at the <a href="https://www.moles.washington.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Molecular Engineering and Sciences Institute</a> and chair of the Department of Chemistry, “for developing new spectroscopy tools for measuring energy flow in molecules and materials with high spatial and temporal resolution.”</li>
<li><a href="https://depts.washington.edu/astron/profile/meadows-victoria/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Victoria Suzanne Meadows</a>, professor of astronomy, “for founding the <a href="http://depts.washington.edu/naivpl/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Virtual Planetary Laboratory</a> and leading the decades-long development of the interdisciplinary modeling framework and community needed to establish the science of exoplanet astrobiology” and “for training the next generation of interdisciplinary scientists who will search for life beyond Earth.”</li>
<li><a href="https://www.aa.washington.edu/facultyfinder/kristi-morgansen" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kristi Morgansen</a>, professor and chair of aeronautics and astronautics, “for leadership and significant advances in nonlinear methods for integrated sensing and control in engineered, bioinspired and biological flight systems” and “for leadership in cross-disciplinary aerospace workforce development.”</li>
<li><a href="https://chem.washington.edu/people/alshakim-nelson" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alshakim Nelson</a>, associate professor of chemistry and member faculty with the Molecular Engineering and Sciences Institute, “for exceptional contributions to the development of synthetic polymers and nanomaterials for self-assembly and advanced manufacturing with application in sustainability, medicine and microelectronics.”</li>
<li>Dr. <a href="https://www.engr.washington.edu/news/article/2020-10-28/tueng-shen-associate-dean" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Tueng Shen</a>, Associate Dean of Medical Technology Innovation in the College of Engineering and the School of Medicine, the Graham and Brenda Siddall Endowed Chair in Cornea Research, and medical director of the UW Eye Institute, “for developing and providing first class clinical treatment of severe corneal blindness to hundreds of people, for establishing the world premier artificial cornea program in Washington, and for leading collaborative research to translate innovative engineering technologies into creative clinical solution.”</li>
<li>Dr. <a href="https://aid.uw.edu/faculty/wesley-c-van-voorhis-md-phd" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wesley Van Voorhis</a>, professor of medicine and director of the <a href="https://cerid.uw.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Center for Emerging and Re-emerging Infectious Diseases</a>, “for global recognition as an authority on drug and vaccine development for viral and parasitic diseases through work as an infectious disease physician and immunologist.”</li>
<li>Dr. <a href="https://depts.washington.edu/anesth/research/labs/vavilala/vavilala-bio.shtml" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Monica Vavilala</a>, professor of pediatrics and of anesthesiology and pain medicine, and director of the <a href="https://hiprc.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Harborview Injury Prevention and Research Center</a>, “for outstanding leadership in pediatric anesthesiology and in the care of children with traumatic brain injury” and “for internationally recognized expertise in traumatic brain injury and direction of the Harborview Injury Prevention and Research Center for the last decade as an exceptional mentor and visionary leader.”</li>
</ul>
<p>UW members who will join the Washington State Academy of Sciences by virtue of their election to one of the National Academies are:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.biostat.washington.edu/people/patrick-heagerty" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Patrick Heagerty</a>, professor of biostatistics, “for the development of novel statistical models for longitudinal data to better diagnose disease, track its trajectory, and predict its outcomes” and “for revolutionizing how dynamic predictors are judged by their discrimination and calibration and has significantly advanced methods for randomized controlled trials.” Heagerty was elected to the National Academy of Medicine in 2021.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.cs.washington.edu/people/faculty/karlin" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Anna Karlin</a>, the Bill and Melinda Gates Chair in Computer Science and Engineering, “for foundational contributions to the mathematics of computer systems and of the internet, as well as to the design and probabilistic analysis of algorithms, especially on-line algorithms, and algorithmic mechanism design and game theory.” Karlin was elected to the National Academy of Sciences in 2021.</li>
<li><a href="https://amath.washington.edu/people/randy-leveque" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Randall LeVeque</a>, professor emeritus of applied mathematics and data science fellow at the <a href="https://escience.washington.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">eScience Institute</a>, “for inventing key algorithms for hyperbolic conservation laws and transforming them into powerful numerical technologies” and “for creating the Clawpack package, which underpins a wide range of application codes in everyday use, such as for hazard assessment due to tsunamis and other geophysical phenomena.” LeVeque was elected to the National Academy of Sciences in 2021.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.biology.washington.edu/people/profile/julie-theriot" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Julie Theriot</a>, the Benjamin D. Hall Endowed Chair in Basic Life Sciences and an investigator with the Howard Hughes Medical Institute, “for advancing our physical understanding of cell motility and growth in animals and bacteria” and “for discovering how the pathogen <em>Listeria</em> uses actin polymerization to move inside human cells, how crawling animal cells coordinate actomyosin dynamics and the mechanical basis of size control and daughter cell separation in bacteria.” Theriot was elected to the National Academy of Sciences in 2021.</li>
<li><a href="https://sites.uw.edu/biostr/people/faculty/rachel-o-wong/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Rachel Wong</a>, professor and chair of biological structure, “for elucidating cellular transformations through which neurons pattern their dendrites, and the interplay of activity-dependent and -independent mechanisms leading to assembly of stereotyped circuits” and “for revelations regarding the fundamental principles of neuronal development through the application of an elegant combination of <em>in vivo</em> imaging, physiology, ultrastructure and genetics to the vertebrate retina.” Wong was elected to the National Academy of Sciences in 2021<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>New members to the Washington State Academy of Sciences are scheduled to be inducted at a meeting in September.</p>
<p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F16%2Fwsas-2021%2F&amp;linkname=20%20UW%20researchers%20elected%20to%20the%20Washington%20State%20Academy%20of%20Sciences%20for%202021" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_twitter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/twitter?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F16%2Fwsas-2021%2F&amp;linkname=20%20UW%20researchers%20elected%20to%20the%20Washington%20State%20Academy%20of%20Sciences%20for%202021" title="Twitter" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_reddit a2a_counter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/reddit?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F16%2Fwsas-2021%2F&amp;linkname=20%20UW%20researchers%20elected%20to%20the%20Washington%20State%20Academy%20of%20Sciences%20for%202021" title="Reddit" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F16%2Fwsas-2021%2F&amp;linkname=20%20UW%20researchers%20elected%20to%20the%20Washington%20State%20Academy%20of%20Sciences%20for%202021" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_print" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/print?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F16%2Fwsas-2021%2F&amp;linkname=20%20UW%20researchers%20elected%20to%20the%20Washington%20State%20Academy%20of%20Sciences%20for%202021" title="Print" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F16%2Fwsas-2021%2F&#038;title=20%20UW%20researchers%20elected%20to%20the%20Washington%20State%20Academy%20of%20Sciences%20for%202021" data-a2a-url="https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/07/16/wsas-2021/" data-a2a-title="20 UW researchers elected to the Washington State Academy of Sciences for 2021"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<enclosure url="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2020/07/16150934/20200515_May-Campus-1112-Edit-Edit_web-150x150.jpg" length="7741" type="image/jpeg" />	</item>
		<item>
		<title>From &#8216;distress&#8217; to &#8216;unscathed&#8217; — mental health of UW students during spring 2020</title>
		<link>https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/07/13/mental-health-of-uw-students-during-spring-2020/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sarah McQuate]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2021 18:37:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Health and medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social science]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Anind Dey]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[College of Arts & Sciences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[College of Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[COVID-19]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[COVID-19 studies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Electrical & Computer Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Department of Psychology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Eve Riskin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Information School]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jennifer Mankoff]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kevin Kuehn]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Margaret Morris]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science & Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Paula Nurius]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Social Work]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.washington.edu/news/?p=74960</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[To understand how the UW's transition to online-only classes affected college students' mental health in the spring of 2020, UW researchers surveyed 147 UW undergraduates over the 2020 spring quarter.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_74961" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="width: 760px"><a href="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/07/13113131/xps-7ZWVnVSaafY-unsplash.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full-content wp-image-74961" src="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/07/13113131/xps-7ZWVnVSaafY-unsplash-750x600.jpg" alt="A table in the living room with a cup of tea, a laptop and a stack of books on top. Behind the table is a couch and a bike" width="750" height="600" srcset="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/07/13113131/xps-7ZWVnVSaafY-unsplash-750x600.jpg 750w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/07/13113131/xps-7ZWVnVSaafY-unsplash-300x240.jpg 300w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/07/13113131/xps-7ZWVnVSaafY-unsplash-1024x819.jpg 1024w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/07/13113131/xps-7ZWVnVSaafY-unsplash-375x300.jpg 375w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/07/13113131/xps-7ZWVnVSaafY-unsplash-1140x912.jpg 1140w" sizes="(max-width: 750px) 100vw, 750px" /></a></p>
<p class="wp-caption-text">To understand how the UW&#8217;s transition to online-only classes affected college students&#8217; mental health in the spring of 2020, UW researchers surveyed 147 UW undergraduates over the 2020 spring quarter.<a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/7ZWVnVSaafY"><span class="wp-media-credit">Unsplash</span></a></span></p>
</div>
<p>In early March 2020, the University of Washington became the first four-year U.S. university to <a href="https://www.washington.edu/news/2020/03/06/uw-classes-moving-online-beginning-march-9/">transition to online-only classes</a> due to the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
<p><a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/doiLanding?doi=10.1037%2Famp0000707">Many researchers predicted</a> severe consequences of these physical distancing measures. To understand how this change affected college students&#8217; mental health, UW researchers surveyed 147 UW students over the 2020 spring quarter, which began shortly after the university transitioned to online-only classes. The team compared the students&#8217; responses to a previous survey of 253 students in spring quarter 2019.</p>
<p>The researchers didn&#8217;t see much change in average levels of students&#8217; depressive symptoms, anxiety, stress or loneliness between 2019 and 2020 or between the beginning and the end of spring quarter 2020. But these average values were masking large differences in students&#8217; individual pandemic experiences. In general, students who used more problem-focused forms of coping — creating plans, focusing on positive aspects, etc. — experienced fewer mental health symptoms than those who disengaged or ignored a situation that was bothering them.</p>
<p>The researchers <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0251580">published these findings</a> June 28 in PLOS ONE.</p>
<p>&#8220;During the pandemic, the challenges of online learning were entwined with social isolation, family demands and socioeconomic pressures,&#8221; said lead author <a href="https://ischool.uw.edu/people/faculty/profile/margiemm">Margaret Morris</a>, an affiliate associate professor in the UW Information School. &#8220;There’s not a simple answer to the question of how students were affected: Some experienced intense distress while others were unscathed.&#8221;</p>
<p>For the past four years, this team has spent spring quarter studying what factors contribute to undergraduates&#8217; overall mental health and well-being. Students are invited to continue participating in each spring quarter study, and the researchers also recruit new students each time. In a previous paper, the researchers found that experiencing <a href="https://www.washington.edu/news/2019/11/04/single-discrimination-events-alter-college-students-daily-behavior/">discrimination events</a> altered student behavior, such as the amount of sleep or exercise a student got following the event.</p>
<p>For the 2020 cohort, the team used three different survey methods to monitor student health. First, they sent large surveys at the beginning and end of spring quarter. Then participants received two shorter surveys each week that asked them to reflect on how they felt — in terms of stress, loneliness, depressive symptoms — in the moment.</p>
<p>In general, students who reported more mental health symptoms at the beginning of the pandemic continued to experience elevated symptoms during the pandemic.</p>
<p>“Problem-focused coping protected students from the harmful effects of stress (anxiety and depression, for example), even though students who used more problem-focused strategies reported more stress,&#8221; said co-author <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/kevin-kuehn-4014b1163/">Kevin Kuehn</a>, a UW doctoral student in clinical psychology.</p>
<p>&#8220;What these findings suggest is that students who coped by actively confronting their challenges, rather than avoiding them, still experienced highly stressful events over the course of the pandemic. However, they were protected from the mental health consequences,&#8221; Kuehn said. &#8220;It may not always feel pleasant or easy to confront the challenges of daily life, particularly during a pandemic, but doing so is likely to be highly beneficial in terms of reducing anxiety and depressive symptoms.&#8221;</p>
<p>Finally, at the end of spring quarter, the team conducted 90-minute in-depth interviews over Zoom with a subset of participants to gain deeper insight into their experiences.</p>
<p>The students described a range of challenges that interfered with learning:</p>
<ul>
<li>Decreased interaction with faculty and peers — students mentioned that having fewer opportunities to interact with faculty and peers left them feeling less engaged. Some students said they felt like part-time students, even when they had full course loads</li>
<li>No shared learning environments — students spoke longingly of a table in a dorm or a spot in the library where they used to gather with classmates for impromptu study sessions</li>
<li>Family needs — family members&#8217; requests or noise often interrupted studying and even test-taking. Family needs, such as caregiving, were a particular challenge to learning for first-generation college students</li>
<li>Interrupted autonomy — some students felt &#8220;trapped&#8221; back at home and described difficult &#8220;power dynamics&#8221; with their parents</li>
<li>Well-being and mental health — many students described disrupted sleep, decreased motivation, and said that they felt depressed or anxious for periods of time. Students&#8217; feelings of detachment from school sometimes contributed to depression. Similarly, worry about grades sometimes cascaded into anxiety and insomnia that, in turn, made it harder to focus</li>
</ul>
<p>Students also developed strategies to combat these challenges, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>Self-learning — students used independent online research to figure out answers to their questions and made up their own experiments to explore what they were learning in class</li>
<li>Structuring routines and environments — many students created fixed schedules for studying or used physical calendars to mark timelines and assignments</li>
<li>Learning with peers — students created remote study groups and held informal remote co-working sessions that combined homework with personal conversations, which helped keep them on task</li>
<li>Participating more in online spaces — many students found it less daunting to ask questions in online classes than in large lecture halls, others found it easier to participate in online office hours and meetings with advisers</li>
<li>Using communication platforms for emotional wellbeing — some students used telehealth or meditation apps, but almost all of them used video communication to check in with their friends. Students emphasized that these connections were critical for their mental health</li>
</ul>
<p>&#8220;On an optimistic note, students are emerging with critical skills for learning and maintaining connectedness with peers over a distance,&#8221; Morris said. &#8220;These active coping skills, which include things such as initiating virtual co-working sessions, leveraging online functions to participate in class and checking in on friends in an emotionally sensitive way, will have continued value as we resume in-person and hybrid models of education.&#8221;</p>
<p>The team plans to follow students through all four years of their time at the UW. The first study cohort graduated this year, and the second cohort will graduate in spring 2022.</p>
<p>Additional co-authors are Jennifer Brown, an alumnus of the UW school of public health who is the research coordinator for this project; <a href="https://socialwork.uw.edu/faculty/professors/paula-s-nurius">Paula Nurius</a>, a professor in the UW School of Social Work; <a href="https://make4all.org/portfolio/han-zhang/">Han Zhang</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ysefidgar/">Yasaman Sefidgar</a>, UW doctoral students in the Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science &amp; Engineering; <a href="https://orsonxu.com/">Xuhai Xu</a>, a doctoral student in the Information School; <a href="https://people.ece.uw.edu/riskin/">Eve Riskin</a>, a UW professor of electrical and computer engineering; <a href="https://ischool.uw.edu/people/faculty/profile/anind">Anind Dey</a>, professor and dean of the UW Information School; <a href="https://www.consolvo.org/">Sunny Consolvo</a>, a researcher at Google; and <a href="https://make4all.org/portfolio/jennifer-mankoff/">Jennifer Mankoff</a>, a professor in the Allen School. This research was funded by the National Science Foundation, the National Institute of Mental Health, Google, the Allen School, UW Department of Electrical &amp; Computer Engineering, the UW College of Engineering and the UW Population Health Initiative.</p>
<p>For more information, contact Morris at <a href="mailto:margiemm@uw.edu">margiemm@uw.edu</a>.</p>
<p>Grant numbers: EDA-2009977, CHS-2016365, CHS-1941537, F31MH117827</p>
<p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F13%2Fmental-health-of-uw-students-during-spring-2020%2F&amp;linkname=From%20%E2%80%98distress%E2%80%99%20to%20%E2%80%98unscathed%E2%80%99%20%E2%80%94%20mental%20health%20of%20UW%20students%20during%20spring%202020" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_twitter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/twitter?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F13%2Fmental-health-of-uw-students-during-spring-2020%2F&amp;linkname=From%20%E2%80%98distress%E2%80%99%20to%20%E2%80%98unscathed%E2%80%99%20%E2%80%94%20mental%20health%20of%20UW%20students%20during%20spring%202020" title="Twitter" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_reddit a2a_counter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/reddit?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F13%2Fmental-health-of-uw-students-during-spring-2020%2F&amp;linkname=From%20%E2%80%98distress%E2%80%99%20to%20%E2%80%98unscathed%E2%80%99%20%E2%80%94%20mental%20health%20of%20UW%20students%20during%20spring%202020" title="Reddit" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F13%2Fmental-health-of-uw-students-during-spring-2020%2F&amp;linkname=From%20%E2%80%98distress%E2%80%99%20to%20%E2%80%98unscathed%E2%80%99%20%E2%80%94%20mental%20health%20of%20UW%20students%20during%20spring%202020" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_print" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/print?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F13%2Fmental-health-of-uw-students-during-spring-2020%2F&amp;linkname=From%20%E2%80%98distress%E2%80%99%20to%20%E2%80%98unscathed%E2%80%99%20%E2%80%94%20mental%20health%20of%20UW%20students%20during%20spring%202020" title="Print" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F07%2F13%2Fmental-health-of-uw-students-during-spring-2020%2F&#038;title=From%20%E2%80%98distress%E2%80%99%20to%20%E2%80%98unscathed%E2%80%99%20%E2%80%94%20mental%20health%20of%20UW%20students%20during%20spring%202020" data-a2a-url="https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/07/13/mental-health-of-uw-students-during-spring-2020/" data-a2a-title="From ‘distress’ to ‘unscathed’ — mental health of UW students during spring 2020"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<enclosure url="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/07/13113131/xps-7ZWVnVSaafY-unsplash-150x150.jpg" length="4333" type="image/jpeg" />	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Drug rebates for insurers tied to higher costs for patients, especially the uninsured</title>
		<link>https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/06/15/drug-rebates-for-insurers-tied-to-higher-costs-for-patients-especially-the-uninsured/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jake Ellison]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 17:41:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Health and medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News releases]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Population Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Public Health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Anirban Basu]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CHOICE Institute]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kai Yeung]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[School of Pharmacy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.washington.edu/news/?p=74707</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Federal agencies that regulate drug pricing and healthcare insurance are concerned that an industry practice of using rebates to lower drug costs for insurers has led to increases in list prices and out-of-pockets costs for patients. To investigate whether patients with or without insurance were paying more because of rebates to insurers, researchers led by...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_74709" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="width: 760px"><a href="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/06/15103736/Wellness-GM-flickr.jpg"><img loading="lazy" class="size-full-content wp-image-74709" src="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/06/15103736/Wellness-GM-flickr-750x500.jpg" alt="" width="750" height="500" srcset="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/06/15103736/Wellness-GM-flickr-750x500.jpg 750w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/06/15103736/Wellness-GM-flickr-300x200.jpg 300w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/06/15103736/Wellness-GM-flickr-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/06/15103736/Wellness-GM-flickr-375x250.jpg 375w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/06/15103736/Wellness-GM-flickr-1140x760.jpg 1140w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/06/15103736/Wellness-GM-flickr.jpg 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 750px) 100vw, 750px" /></a></p>
<p class="wp-caption-text">Researchers have established a link between drug rebates and higher costs to patients.<span class="wp-media-credit">Wellness GM/Flickr</span></span></p>
</div>
<p>Federal agencies that regulate drug pricing and healthcare insurance <a href="https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2020/11/30/2020-25841/fraud-and-abuse-removal-of-safe-harbor-protection-for-rebates-involving-prescription-pharmaceuticals">are concerned</a> that an industry practice of using rebates to lower drug costs for insurers has led to increases in list prices and out-of-pockets costs for patients.</p>
<p>To investigate whether patients with or without insurance were paying more because of rebates to insurers, researchers led by the University of Washington examined cost and price data on more than 400 branded drugs. The <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/2780950">study</a> found that rebates were associated with increases in out-of-pocket costs for patients by an average of $6 for those with commercial insurance, $13 for Medicare patients and $39 for the uninsured.</p>
<p>“We know that list prices have been increasing quite dramatically as have rebates, but no one has looked into the association between rebates and out-of-pocket costs,” said study lead author <a href="https://sop.washington.edu/people/kai-yeung/">Kai Yeung</a>, an affiliate assistant professor at the <a href="https://sop.washington.edu/choice/">CHOICE Institute</a> in the UW School of Pharmacy. “Increases in out-of-pocket costs are associated with rebates, however rebates also help keep premium costs down.”</p>
<p>Consequently, said Yeung, who is also an assistant professor at Kaiser Permanente Bernard J. Tyson School of Medicine, “There has been inadequate focus on the impact the pricing mechanism has on the uninsured, who are most affected.”</p>
<p>For the <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/2780950">study published June 14 in JAMA</a>, the researchers used data on 444 branded drugs without generic equivalents from national datasets involving healthcare costs and drug prices from 2007 to 2018 including the federal <a href="https://meps.ahrq.gov/survey_comp/household.jsp">Medical Expenditure Panel Survey</a> and <a href="https://www.ssrhealth.com/">SSR Health</a>, a private company that collects and analyzes prescription drug pricing data.</p>
<p>Researchers point out that the cost increases can impact patient health, since higher costs can cause patients to take their medication less often. That, in turn, can lead to increased emergency room use and hospitalizations. People in their study who did not have insurance had the poorest health and those with lower incomes were less likely to take medication as prescribed when costs increased.</p>
<p>“Further,” the researchers wrote, “uninsured individuals were more likely to be in racial minority groups, amplifying pre-existing disparities in healthcare access.”</p>
<p>As a result, the authors suggest future research and policies should focus on decoupling list prices from what patients pay out of pocket, “especially for uninsured individuals.”</p>
<p>“The biggest takeaway is understanding that the rebates work to reduce the cost of prescription drugs for insurance companies and may reduce premiums,” said co-author <a href="https://sop.washington.edu/people/anirban-basu/">Anirban Basu</a>, the Stergachis Family endowed director of the CHOICE Institute and professor of health economics at the UW School of Pharmacy. “And while it’s unclear how much the discounts are reducing premiums, they are definitely not translating to lower out-of-pocket costs for the patients who are using the treatment because of this structure of coinsurance and copayments tied to the list price.”</p>
<p>Stacie Dusetzina, Vanderbilt University School of Medicine, Nashville, Tenn., is also a co-author. This research wassupported in part by grant funding from the Donaghue Foundation’s Greater Value Portfolio.</p>
<p>###</p>
<p>For more information, contact Yeung at <a href="mailto:Kai.Yeung@kp.org">Kai.Yeung@kp.org</a> and Basu at <a href="mailto:basua@uw.edu">basua@uw.edu</a>.</p>
<p><a class="a2a_button_facebook" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/facebook?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F06%2F15%2Fdrug-rebates-for-insurers-tied-to-higher-costs-for-patients-especially-the-uninsured%2F&amp;linkname=Drug%20rebates%20for%20insurers%20tied%20to%20higher%20costs%20for%20patients%2C%20especially%20the%20uninsured" title="Facebook" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_twitter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/twitter?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F06%2F15%2Fdrug-rebates-for-insurers-tied-to-higher-costs-for-patients-especially-the-uninsured%2F&amp;linkname=Drug%20rebates%20for%20insurers%20tied%20to%20higher%20costs%20for%20patients%2C%20especially%20the%20uninsured" title="Twitter" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_reddit a2a_counter" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/reddit?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F06%2F15%2Fdrug-rebates-for-insurers-tied-to-higher-costs-for-patients-especially-the-uninsured%2F&amp;linkname=Drug%20rebates%20for%20insurers%20tied%20to%20higher%20costs%20for%20patients%2C%20especially%20the%20uninsured" title="Reddit" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_email" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/email?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F06%2F15%2Fdrug-rebates-for-insurers-tied-to-higher-costs-for-patients-especially-the-uninsured%2F&amp;linkname=Drug%20rebates%20for%20insurers%20tied%20to%20higher%20costs%20for%20patients%2C%20especially%20the%20uninsured" title="Email" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_button_print" href="https://www.addtoany.com/add_to/print?linkurl=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F06%2F15%2Fdrug-rebates-for-insurers-tied-to-higher-costs-for-patients-especially-the-uninsured%2F&amp;linkname=Drug%20rebates%20for%20insurers%20tied%20to%20higher%20costs%20for%20patients%2C%20especially%20the%20uninsured" title="Print" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"></a><a class="a2a_dd addtoany_share_save addtoany_share" href="https://www.addtoany.com/share#url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.washington.edu%2Fcms%2Fnews%2F2021%2F06%2F15%2Fdrug-rebates-for-insurers-tied-to-higher-costs-for-patients-especially-the-uninsured%2F&#038;title=Drug%20rebates%20for%20insurers%20tied%20to%20higher%20costs%20for%20patients%2C%20especially%20the%20uninsured" data-a2a-url="https://www.washington.edu/news/2021/06/15/drug-rebates-for-insurers-tied-to-higher-costs-for-patients-especially-the-uninsured/" data-a2a-title="Drug rebates for insurers tied to higher costs for patients, especially the uninsured"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<enclosure url="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2021/06/15103736/Wellness-GM-flickr-150x150.jpg" length="3605" type="image/jpeg" />	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
